Guide to the Edgar R. Baker Papers 1926-2011 (bulk, 1940s-1969) MS 3156
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Subject Files, 1926-2011 (bulk, 1930s-1960s); 1.5 Linear feet
  - TLI Matters (3 folders), 1959 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    Includes itineraries and some invitations and related documents for Baker, accompanied by his wife, on their March-April global business trip to Japan, Vietnam (Saigon), Singapore, India, London, Berlin, and Paris; Baker's remarks titled "Two Proposals for Economic Cooperation in Southeast Asia" delivered at the 12th annual Far East Conference in New York, with program, two photographs, and report of proceedings; clipping from the NY Times of Baker's book review of "Power without Property" by Adolf A. Berle, Jr.; publicity booklet for the Chicago International Fair & Exposition; Economic Club of New York program and head table chart; and clippings.
  - TLI Matters, 1950s? (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Includes three undated speeeches, one titled "Portrait of America," a second concerning U.S.-Asia relations, and a third in rough handwritten form on the role of the U.S. in the world economy; a flyer publicizing Baker's appearance at the Toledo World Trade Week luncheon; a witty poem about Baker's travels; and some FYIs.
  - TLI Matters, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Includes Baker's remarks titled "Future Trends in International Economics" delivered to the Chamber of Commerce of Greater Philadelphia, with program and panelist biographies; remarks titled "The Outlook for the World Economy" delivered in St. Louis; an issue of "The General Electric Defense Quarterly" with remarks about public understanding and its effect on defense policy by a panel of TIME executives, including Baker; the booklet "Time Incorporated: An Informal History"; FYIs and press releases on TLI and Time reorganizations; and an undated (circa 1960?) letter from "Dave" writing about TLI matters in Japan.
  - TLI Matters, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    The file holds only a few documents from these years including, from 1962, a report on South Africa generally and TLI's distributor, Central News Agency, in particular; and the report for one week of London circulation; and a few other documents.
  - Promotions and Congratulatory Letters, 1965-1966, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    The 1968 item is Baker's biographical statement as Vice President, Time Inc. and Director of Corporate Development, Time Inc.
  - TIME Matters, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Includes proposals to the Time Inc Board to create an educational joint venture with General Electric (1965) and to purchase New York Graphic Society (1966). Also Baker's article "The American Magazine Overseas" in "The George Washington University Magazine."
  - TIME Matters, 1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    1967: Includes documents concerning the MGM transaction and a proposal to acquire the Newark (N.J.) Evening News. Several undated documents are likely from the 1960s and include 3 itineraries and guest lists and a transcript of Baker's remarks to an unidentified audience.
  - News Clippings, 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Matters, 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Includes various documents not related to TLI: One sheet of stationery from New York Citizens for Kennedy and Johnson, with Baker listed as a Co-Chairman (1960?); a George Washington University (GWU) Fund Drive report on which Baker appears as the New York Chairman (1960); a biography of Baker apparently sent to the White House in connection with a possible appointment in the Kennedy administration, with telegram from Baker to his wife suggesting as much (1961); letter to Baker indicating he was awarded GWU's Alumni Achievement Award (1962); newsletter announcing Baker being named Chairman of GWU's annual fundraising drive (1963); and Baker's election to the GWU board as an alumni trustee and member of its council for arts and sciences (1967).
  - Obituaries and Eulogies, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Some of the documents are in Japanese.
  - Post-Mortem, 1978-2011 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Includes items saved by, presumably, Alice Baker after Edgar's death. The principal item in this folder is a 15 page note to TIME historian Curt Prendergast expanding on some of the recollections Alice had shared wth him a few months earlier in an interview (1980). A 2011 note from Edgar's sister, Mildred Bowers, to her children expresses some of her thoughts about Edgar and the records he and Alice had left behind. Other items are a few clippings and tearsheets about Time and other matters that struck the compiler as related to Edgar's work and legacy.
- Series III. Correspondence, Personal, 1942-1971; 1 Linear feet
  The series includes extensive personal correspondence of Edgar Baker. A substantial portion of this was written by Baker during his business trips for TIME-LIFE International, most to his wife Alice, but many to his mother, Ida, or other family members, including his grandmother, Elizabeth, called "Bamma." In these letters, Baker described his impressions of the country and its culture as well as his travel experiences. The richest and most extensive of these relate to Baker's 1947 months-long worldwide trip, and he writes from Australia, New Zealand, India, and other countries in that part of the world. 1947 also holds many letters Alice sent to Edgar during his trip.
  The series also holds letters that Baker received from a few other correspondents. The most extensive of these letters came from two women: Jane Alden and June Bourke. According to a note in the file written by Alice, Alden was a girlfriend of Baker's in college and they reconnected at least for a time around 1949 when she worked for the U.S. State Department as a research analyst specializing in Japan. Bourke lived in London and Baker seems to have had a serious romantic relationship with her in the mid-late 1950s. Many letters from both women are in the series in which they discuss their activiities, the relationship, and generally express their affections.
  Among the other correspondence is one 1962 letter from Ralph Bunche acknowledging Baker's letter of support for Bunche's potential Senate campaign and one 1968 letter from Hubert Humphrey (water damaged) thanking Baker for his support in the failed Presidential campaign. Various other correspondents send acknowlegements of gifts and other courtesies and social pleasantries. One letter is in French.
  Finally, there are two large sets of correspondence centered on Baker's 1963 heart attack suffered while he and Alice were in Rome and on Baker's death in 1969. Most of the 1963 letters express get-well-soon wishes, but others relate to medical matters, arrangements for the Bakers's return home by ship, and the like. In addition to condolence letters to Alice, the 1969 files include documents related to the funding of an adjunct professor position in public and international affairs at George Washington University in Baker's memory.
  Though the bulk of personal correspondence is in this series, some of the documents in Series I are of a personal nature. Most especially, there are several letters between Baker, his brother Don, and various businesses, lawyers and banks regarding estate settlement of his aunt, Irma B. Hoffman, as Edgar was the Estate Administrator.
  The series is arranged with family correspondents in chronological order, followed by others, then the get-well/heart attack and condolence letters.
  - Family Correspondents, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    3 letters from Edgar to his mother, writing from Mexico in August, describing his travels.
  - Family Correspondents, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes many letters from Alice, writing to Edgar during her stay in Florida with her relatives, Mr and Mrs Newton Merrill. Over the course of about 5 weeks, Alice wrote often about her activities there. Also a letter from Edgar's grandmother, Elizabeth ("Bamma"), and one from his sister, Mildred, both to Edgar and Alice.
  - Family Correspondents, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Includes 5 letters, dating from May-June. Edgar and Alice had traveled to Mexico together on a combination business and pleasure trip. Edgar traveled on to Guatamala and elsewhere in the region, while Alice remained in Mexico where her parents joined her. One letter is from Edgar to his parents describing his trip as he flew from Mexico to Guatemala. The other 4 letters are from Alice to Edgar (2), Edgar's mother (1), and someone at Winter Haven, all discussing her stay in Mexico.
  - Family Correspondents. Edgar to Alice, 1947 (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 4-8)
    In 1947, Baker took a lengthy worldwide business trip, including Australia, New Zealand, Netherlands East Indies (NEI), India and elsewhere before returning home via Europe. These folders hold many of the letters he sent to Alice during this trip, recounting in some detail his observations and experiences. He attempted to number the letters in sequence, but there are gaps so it is not known if there are letters missing or if Baker misnumbered some, though both are likely. Only letters from February-June (Australia, South Pacific, Southeast Asia, India) are here.
  - Family Correspondents. Edgar to Other Family, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Includes several letters from Edgar to his grandmother, mother, father, and sister (and one to Edgar from his father) written while on his travels in Australia and Southeast Asia.
  - Family Correspondents. Alice to Edgar, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Many letters from Alice to Edgar as he traveled overseas, conveying updates about the family, social gossip, and her own efforts at starting a career. Edgar's father died while Baker was on his long trip and Alice refers to that in at least one of her later letters.
  - Family Correspondents, 1948-49, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes several letters from Edgar and Alice to his mother, grandmother and sister as they traveled in Europe in the late summer of 1948; London, Paris, Isle of Capri, and Geneva are the main datelines. Also, a few letters to Edgar in October from Alice as she returned to the U.S alone and he apparently traveled to Asia. One 1949 letter from Edgar writing from London to his mother.
  - Family Correspondents, 1950-51, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Includes an exchange of one letter each between Edgar and his mother while he was traveling in Tokyo (1950), with his travel itinerary for October-early November. 1951 letters include letters to Edgar from Alice and others (relatives?) regarding her travels and other matters in Europe in the spring. In the summer she connects with Edgar and they traveled in Eastern Europe, Greece, and the Mideast; there are three letters from them to Edgar's mother, with the travel itinerary.
  - Family Correspondents, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Includes three letters from Edgar in Tokyo to Alice and his mother, with related Time press release and clippings.
  - Family Correspondents, 1957,1959 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Includes 4 letters and 1 postcard from Edgar to his mother, writing from Florence (1947), Saigon, Egypt, and Warsaw.
  - Family Correspondents, 1962-64, 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Includes twelve letters and postcards from Edgar to his mother as he traveled in London and Spain (1962), in 1963 with Alice in South Africa, and in 1964 in Eastern Europe. In October 1963, Edgar suffered a heart attack in Rome and a couple of his letters refer to his recovery and his itinerary for the voyage back to New York. One letter is written in response to the assassination of John F. Kennedy.
  - Family Correspondents, undated, 1940s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Includes several letters between Edgar, Alice, his mother, and other likely family members that are undated.
  - Other Correspondents (3 folders), circa 1950-1968 (Box 4, Folder 17-19)
  - Miscellaneous, 1953, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Includes two carbon copies of a sworn statement by Baker attesting that a former government agency colleague had not expressed Communist sympathies; an unattributed carbon copy of a soldier's outline of his movements in World War II Europe at D-Day and after; and a clipping and stamps that became separated from the correspondence.
  - Heart Attack Related (4 folders), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 21-24)
  - Condolences and Related (7 folders), 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 25-31)
- Series IV. Photographs and Memorabilia, 1940s-1960s; 1.5 Linear feet in one flat box and part of a record carton
  The series primarily includes photographs of Edgar Baker either alone (i.e., portraits, passport snapshots) or with others in business or business social settings. His wife, Alice Baker, appears in several of these either as she traveled with him or in the few personal photos here, specifically of the couple at their wedding reception. Most of the settings and other individuals are unidentified and undated, though there is one large set of photos taken at Baker's farewell party from Time-Life International. Two photographs--one of Adlai Stevenson and the other of Henry Luce--are inscribed by them to Baker.
  In addition to photographs, the series holds a scrapbook given Baker by his Time colleagues on the occasion of his 40th birthday in 1960; the object is richly emblematic of the office humor of the period. The series also holds Baker's passports, a "26 Julio" pin of the type associated with the Cuban Revolution, and a few other items of memorabilia, as noted in the container list.
  The series is arranged by format and subject matter.
  - Photographs. Edgar only., 1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photographs. Edgar and Alice Baker, 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Includes wedding day photos, a souvenir photo taken at the Copacabana, arriving in Mexico City (1946), in Venice (1958), and others.
  - Photographs. Edgar and Others, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Includes Baker at conferences, business settings, business social settings, and others. Several are from Asia, including a set in which Baker arrives by helicopter on a building rooftop (likely Tokyo). One photo places him on the set of the MGM film "Alfred the Great."
  - Photographs. Time-Life International Farewell Party, 1965? (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Many photos from the event marking Baker's move from TLI to a corporate management position at Time. Most of the photos taken by LIFE photographer Martha Holmes.
  - Scrapbook. 40th Birthday Gag Gift, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Includes about 40 pages of pictures with humorous comments related to Baker's position at TLI. Originally in binder, but removed for conservation purposes. At rear of binder, now in folder, is a "26 Julio" pin with note suggesting, humorously, that it was to be worn in good health on trips to Cuba.
  - Memorabilia (2 folders), 1940s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    Holds business cards (Time Inc. VP); United Airlines 100,000 Mile Club card; TLI accredited representative card; Associate Member, American Institute of Management certificate; guest of honor certificate from Montevideo, Mexico (1955), in Spanish; honorary citizen of New Orleans certificate (1954); original editorial cartoon by Flora, dated 1959, altered for presentation to Baker in 1966; gag TIME cover featuring Baker as fisherman with catch (1951); 6 passports (1946-68); International Driving Permit (1951); and TWA Royal Ambassador menu (in form of a scroll).
  - Oversize Photographs (flat box), 1940s-1960s (Offsite-box 5)
    Includes these items: mounted photograph of Adlai Stevenson, inscribed and autographed to Baker (1957); mounted color photograph of a drawing of Henry Luce, inscribed and autographed to Baker; Baker with other fishermen showing their catch of sailfish; Baker in his office at Time (circa 1960); and 4 wedding day reception photos of Edgar and Alice.